<TEI>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="format">xml</title>
<title type="subject04">British Philosophy</title>
<title type="language01">English</title>
<title type="collection">The Complete Works and Correspondence of David Hume. Electronic Edition.</title>
<title type="short">Hume: Complete Works and Correspondence</title>    
<title type="book">Edition Information</title>
<author>Hume, David</author>
    <editor></editor>
       </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>InteLex Corporation</publisher>
    <pubPlace>
     <address>
      <addrLine>P.O. Box 859</addrLine>
      <addrLine>Charlottesville, Virginia, 22902-0859, USA</addrLine>
     </address>
    </pubPlace>
    <availability status="restricted">
     <p>Available to institutions via internet access from the publisher.</p>
    </availability>
    <date><num type="year">1995</num></date>
    <idno type="isbn collection">978-1-57085-002-8</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
<titleStmt>
      <title></title>
  <author>Hume, David</author>
      <editor></editor>
     </titleStmt>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher></publisher>
      <pubPlace></pubPlace>
      <date></date>
     </publicationStmt>
        
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc>
    <langUsage xml:lang="GRK"><language ident="GRK">Greek</language></langUsage>
    <langUsage xml:lang="HEB"><language ident="HEB">Hebrew</language></langUsage></profileDesc></teiHeader>
 <text>
<front>
 <div type="pmpreface" xml:id="div.hume.pmpreface.1"><head><figure><graphic url="common/PastMastersPreface.jpg" alt="Past Masters Preface"/></figure><lb/>
  LIST OF CONTENTS</head>
  <p><emph>The Complete Works and Correspondence of David Hume</emph> contains the complete works of David Hume, including his <emph>History of England</emph> and the three published 20th century volumes of Hume's correspondence.</p><lb/>
 
 <p><emph>The Complete Works and Correspondence of David Hume.</emph> Compiled and edited by Mark C. Rooks. Charlottesville: InteLex Corporation, 1995.</p>
 
 <p>Hume, David. <emph>Letters of David Hume.</emph> Edited by J. Y. T. Greig. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1932.</p>
 
 <p>_____. <emph>New Letters of David Hume.</emph> Edited by Raymond Klibansky and Ernest C. Mossner. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1954.</p>
 
 <p>_____. <emph>History of England.</emph> Edited by Frits van Holthoon. 6 vols. Charlottesville: InteLex Corporation, 2000.</p>
  
  <p class="indent_4em">"My Own Life"</p>
  
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>A Treatise of Human Nature</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>An Abstract of A Treatise of Human Nature</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>A Letter from a Gentleman</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>An Enquiry Concerning the Principles of Morals</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>Essays Moral, Political, and Literary</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>A Dissertation of the Passions</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>The Natural History of Religion</emph></p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion</emph></p>
  
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 1</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 2</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 3</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 4</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 5</p>
  
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>History of England, from the Invasion of Julius Caesar to The Revolution in 1688,</emph> Vol. 6</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>Letters of David Hume,</emph> Vol. 1</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>Letters of David Hume,</emph> Vol. 2</p>
  <p class="indent_4em"><emph>New Letters of David Hume</emph></p>
   
   <lb/>
   <p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi>"My Own Life"</hi> was drawn from the 1898 Green and Grose edition. Page numbers identifying folios refer to page numbers found in Green and Grose.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume2
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi><emph rend="italic">A Treatise of Human Nature</emph></hi> was drawn from the 1911 Everyman's Library Edition. The text was carefully checked against the 1886 Green and Grose edition. Page numbers which identify each folio of the <emph rend="italic">Treatise</emph> refer to page numbers of the correlative passage in the Second Edition of Nidditch.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume 3
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of  <hi>"An Abstract of <emph rend="italic">A Treatise of Human Nature</emph>"</hi> is reproduced directly from a facsimile edition of the work. Bibliographic information appears on the volume title page. Page numbers refer to the page numbers of the original edition.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume4
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">This edition of  <hi>"A Letter from a Gentleman"</hi> is reproduced directly from the 1745 Edinburgh edition. Page numbers on reference lines are also from the 1745 edition.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume5
</p>--> <p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi><emph rend="italic">An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</emph></hi> was drawn from the 1898 Green and Grose, but proofread against the 1912 Open Court edition. Discrepancies were arbitrated by the 1758 Hume. The Advertisement was drawn from the Open Court edition. Two page numbers identify each folio: the first, labeled <emph rend="italic">p.</emph>, refers to page numbers in the Third Edition of the Nidditch <emph rend="italic">Enquiry.</emph> The second, labeled <emph rend="italic">gp.</emph>, refers to page numbers in Green and Grose.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume6
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi><emph rend="italic">An Enquiry Concerning the Principles of Morals</emph></hi> was drawn from the 1898 Green and Grose, but proofread against 1854 Works, with word discrepancies checked against the 1758 Hume. Two page numbers identify each folio: the first, labeled <emph rend="italic">p.</emph>, refers to the page number of the correlative passage in the Third Edition of the Nidditch <emph rend="italic">Enquiries</emph>; the second, labeled <emph rend="italic">gp.</emph> refers to the page number in Green and Grose.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume7
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi><emph rend="italic">Essays Moral, Political, and Literary</emph></hi> is a corrected version of the Miller edition (1987) with three exceptions: 1) The bibliographic information included in the footnotes is that of Green and Grose, although the text of the footnotes is that of Miller; Green and Grose altered (primarily added to) bibliographic information in Hume's footnotes; 2) the variant readings are those of Green and Grose, although we have introduced a few changes for reasons of consistency and presentation; and 3) The text of the essays "Of Suicide," and "Of the Immortality of the Soul," is drawn from Green and Grose. Miller and Green and Grose worked from different proof copies of these two essays.
</p><p rend="tbindent">Miller found 100 word and phrase discrepancies, and 175 punctuation discrepancies between Green and Grose and the 1777 Hume. Miller also used the 1772 Hume to check typographical errors in the 1777 Hume. Hence our reliance upon Miller. We are indebted to Prof. Miller and the Liberty Fund for their kindly consenting to our use of their text. Prof. Miller's extensive editorial additions do not appear in this edition.
</p><p rend="tbindent">Two page numbers appear on the reference line for each folio: <emph rend="italic">mp.</emph> refers to the page number in Miller, and <emph rend="italic">gp.</emph> refers to the page number in Green and Grose.
</p><p rend="tbindent">The reference line for the <emph rend="italic">Essays</emph> gives the ESY abbreviation indicating the work, the section of the <emph rend="italic">Essays</emph> (Pt. 1, Pt. 2, Wdrawn, or Unpub.), the number of the essay (E. 1, E. 2, etc.) and the paragraph and page number of the folio.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume8
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi>"A Dissertation on the Passions,"</hi> is drawn from the 1898 Green and Grose Edition. The page numbers in the reference lines of the folios refer to page numbers in Green and Grose.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume9
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of this edition of <hi><emph rend="italic">The Natural History of Religion,</emph></hi> is a corrected version of the 1898 Green and Grose. The page numbers which appear in the reference line of the folios refer to page numbers in Green and Grose.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume10
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">The text of <hi><emph rend="italic">Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion</emph></hi> is a corrected version of the 1854 Works. The page numbers which identify each folio, refer to the Kemp Smith <emph rend="italic">Dialogues.</emph>
</p><!--<p>HUME Volumes 11-17
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">Hume's <hi><emph rend="italic">History of England</emph></hi> is a new variorum edition edited by Prof. Frits van Holthoon. The base text is the edition of 1778, from which the Liberty Classics edition was created. Page numbers are also from the edition of 1778 (duplicated in the Liberty Classics edition). For a complete discussion of the text, see the introduction by the editor at the beginning of the first volume of Hume's <emph rend="italic">History of England</emph>.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume 18
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">This is the 1932 two-volume edition of <hi><emph rend="italic">The Letters of David Hume</emph></hi> (Oxford, Clarendon Press) edited by J. Y. T. Greig. Page numbers on reference line are from the 193 edition.
</p><!--<p>HUME Volume19
</p>--><p rend="tbindent">This is the 1954 edition of <hi><emph rend="italic">New Letters of David Hume</emph></hi> (Oxford, Clarendon Press), edited by Raymond Klibansky and Ernest Mossner. Page numbers on reference lines are from the 1954 edition.
</p><lb/></div></front><body><p></p></body><back></back></text></TEI>
